<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest and just apology for; or, defence of the present East-India-Company Against the accusations of their adversaries. Wherein the crimes alledged against them, are fairly examined; the calumny's confuted, and all submitted to the judgment of impartial and unprejudiced persons.</title>
            <author>Tenche, Nathaniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T34A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825516</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825516</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2099:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest and just apology for; or, defence of the present East-India-Company Against the accusations of their adversaries. Wherein the crimes alledged against them, are fairly examined; the calumny's confuted, and all submitted to the judgment of impartial and unprejudiced persons.</title>
                  <author>Tenche, Nathaniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed anno Domini, MDCXC. [1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: N.T., i.e. Nathaniel Tenche.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Marsh's Library, Dublin, Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29900:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29900:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MODEST and JUST APOLOGY FOR; OR, DEFENCE OF THE PRESENT <hi>Eaſt-India-Company.</hi> AGAINST THE ACCUSATIONS OF THEIR ADVERSARIES. Wherein the CRIMES alledged againſt them, are fairly Examined; The CALUMNY's Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and all ſubmitted to the Judgment of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial and Unprejudiced <hi>PERSONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29900:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29900:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>THIS Apology was drawn up ſome little time before the laſt Prorogation of the late Parliament; though upon ſome Reaſons, forborn to be publiſht, which I thought it neceſſary to give you notice of; leſt finding ſome Paſſages therein adapted to that time, you may think them ſomething improper, as to the preſent: You will not find in this any particular notice taken, of any of thoſe many Papers, by their Enemies publiſhed abroad to defame them, (except the Preamble of their own Subſcriptions) which indeed was induſtriouſly avoided: They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo filled with ſcurrilous Language, and opprobrious Expreſſions, that they deſerve no Anſwer: What hath been here endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is to relate matter of Fact truly (leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to make the Inference) which I have not willingly falſified in any one particular: If any ſuch ſhould be, I do declare, it hath
<pb facs="tcp:29900:3"/>bin through inadvertency, and not deſigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The whole is ſubmitted to the cenſure of the unprejudiced Perſon, which being fairly and impartially conſidered, together with the Circumſtances attending thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Actions here diſcourſed of: I doubt not, but the ſuppoſed Monſter, will not now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, ſo black and ugly, as he hath bin of late depainted: It is poſſible, That theſe Papers may meet with a Reply: For I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect they will ſatisfie every one: But if ſuch be their fate, If the ſaid Reply be managed with Candour and Ingenuity, they ſhall have from me a fair acknowledgment of my Error, where it is ſo; or a fair Rejoynder where it is otherwayes. But if it be filled with ſuch ſcurrilous Language, as thoſe Papers have bin, which of late have bin expoſed to the Publick againſt them: Let the matter be what it will, It ſhall receive no other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer from me, than the reſt have done, <hi>viz.</hi> Contempt and Silence. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29900:3"/>
            <head>A Modeſt and Juſt Apology for, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the preſent <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHAT great and indefatigable induſtry hath bin imployed? What Arts and Devices made uſe of, to blaſt the Reputation of the preſent <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>-Company, is notoriouſly evident to all, who either give themſelves the trouble of liſtning to thoſe Calumnies, dayly inculcated in all noted Coffee-Houſes againſt them, or to the reading of thoſe Prints expoſed publickly, and delivered <hi>gratis</hi> in the ſaid Coffee-Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to all ſuch as will but accept them: Wherein the ſaid Company are not only ſet forth to be Bankrupts as to their preſent Condition, but repreſented as vile and odious as Malice it ſelf can invent, or a Pen dipt in the very gall of Aſps can depaint; ſo that it may juſtly ſeem neceſſary, that at this time a juſt and modeſt Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, and their preſent Condition from the ſaid Aſpertions ſhould be publiſhed; and the rather ſince their Enemies have endeavoured of late to impoſe, not only upon the unthinking Vulgar, but upon the Members of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, by putting Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers into their hands; wherein beſides the ſcurrility of the Language ſutable to the Authors, there are many things notoriouſly untrue; nay they have preſumed ſo far up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole Body of the Legiſlative Power of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, King, Lords and Commons, as to declare to them,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29900:4"/>in the <hi>preamble</hi> to their <hi>new Subſcriptions,</hi> by them now Printed and Publiſhed, the very terms of an Act of Parliament to be by them paſſed, without which, their Subſcriptions are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void, and no wayes obliging, and withal are become ſo confident, as to publiſh to the World their Aſſurance, that an Act ſhall paſs in ſuch terms, as they have there preſcribed, which withal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is left to a juſt cenſure.</p>
            <p>It is now confeſſed almoſt by all, even the very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the preſent Company, That the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade is of a great National advantage; That for the making of it more advantagious, it muſt be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on in a Joynt Stock: That that Stock muſt be in a Company excluſive to all Interlopers: That a Joynt Stock and Interlopers, are things inconſiſtent: That ſuch a Company muſt neceſſarily be inveſted with Powers ſufficient to govern their reſpective Reſidences abroad, and carry on their Trade; So that theſe things being ſufficiently evident to common ſenſe, and now by almoſt all in general acknowledged, it will be needleſs to bring any Arguments for the proof of them; by which means the buſineſs of this preſent Paper will be much contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and applyed only to undeceive the World, in ſome of thoſe Calumnies, by which the Enemies of the preſent Company have endeavoured to blacken them, and render them moſt obnoxious to the Publick; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhall be as conciſe as poſſible I can, without ſo much as in the leaſt taking notice in particular of that ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Language and opprobious Expreſſions, they are pleaſed to caſt upon them.</p>
            <p>The firſt Objection then that preſents it ſelf to Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and which hath created them ſo many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, is, That the ſaid Company have at ſeveral times given diſturbance to thoſe Perſons, who traded into the places of their Priviledge, and were not free of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29900:4"/>ſaid Company, and are therefore ſtiled Interlopers, and that, by ſtopping their Ships and Goods, and by other ways and means to the hindrance of their Trade.</p>
            <p>To this it is anſwered, That the Premiſes before laid down fairly conſidered, and which are now in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner univerſally acknowledged, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Trade of <hi>India</hi> to render it Nationally advantagious, muſt be carryed on in a Joynt Stock; That the ſaid Trade in this Nation hath been ſo carried on all along in a Joynt Stock, excluſive to all others not free of the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, by vertue of, and under the Power of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the ſeveral Princes of this Realm, ever ſince the Trade was firſt eſtabliſhed; That a Joynt Stock and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terloping are wholly inconſiſtent; And that the preſent Company had the ſame Trade wholly and entirely gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them equally with their Predeceſſors, from the lawful and undoubted Soveraigns of this Realm: I ſay theſe things fairly and impartially conſidered, It will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear no more injuſtice in this preſent Company, to put all ſtops and Inconveniences they could upon all Perſons not free of the ſaid Company, attempting to break in upon them, by trading into the parts of their Priviledge ſo granted to them as aforeſaid, than it would be in a private Perſon to defend himſelf from the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of thoſe, who would wrong him in his Perſon or Eſtate, and by force endeavour to wreſt him out of the Poſſeſſion of his Freehold: Nay it may truly and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be affirmed, That had not the Managers of the ſaid Stock exerted all the Powers granted them in their Charters, to the keeping out of all unfree Perſons from breaking into their Trade, they had been unfaithful to the Truſt repoſed in them by the Generality, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers of the Intereſt both of themſelves, and of the Nation. For whatever Company for the future may or ſhall be eſtabliſhed (if the Wiſdom of the Nation ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29900:5"/>think ſit to make any Alteration,) unleſs they have Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers granted, and Liberty as occaſion ſhall offer to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert them, to keep out Interlopers, and ſecure the Trade intirely to the Joynt Stock, they can never preſerve that Trade to themſelves or the Nation. And ſince it is now almoſt generally confeſſed, and is moſt certainly true, That if the Wiſdom of the Nation ſhall think fit to eſtabliſh this or any other Company by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, If they will inable them to carry on the ſaid Trade to a National advantage, they muſT grant them the ſame, if not an increaſe of that <hi>Power</hi> which the preſent <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>-Company have granted to them by their Charter, Wherein then is the great Crime which the preſent Company is guilty off? And hath created them ſo many bitter and implacable Enemies? In ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Interlopers Ships, and giving them what diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance they could in their Trade, ſince either there muſt be no Company and Joynt Stock, or all Interloping muſt be excluded? All Mankind being agreed, that both can't conſiſt at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>To this I preſume it will be anſwer'd, That the thing in it ſelf, for a Company eſtabliſht in a Joynt Stock to obſtruct all others, may not be criminal, becauſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and rational: But that this preſent Company have either exceeded the Powers granted to them in their Charters, Or if they have not exceeded them, Their Charters themſelves are not agreeable to Law, and ſo they are criminal in acting by an unlawful Power. I ſhall therefore now fairly conſider, how far the preſent Company is criminal in either of theſe two reſpects.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, That the preſent Company have exceeded the Powers granted to them by their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, It is wholly denyed by them, That they have at any time exceeded the Powers given them therein, by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29900:5"/>any of their Actions here at home, Or by any Orders given by them to their Servants abroad. And this being matter of fact, muſt reſt upon the proof of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainants; and that being to be in particulars, as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in caſes of matter of fact; The charge will then appear, either to be true or falſe, when the matter of the Complaint being firſt fully proved, and the Powers granted to the ſaid Company, being likewiſe fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and both compared together, Then I ſay it will be clearly ſeen, and not before, Whether the preſent Company have exceeded the Powers therein granted, which is the firſt Objection. But it being the buſineſs of this Apology to be as conciſe as may be, there is no room left to enter upon Particulars; Only by the way it may ſeem to incline any rational Man to believe, that they themſelves are very doubtful of the Truth of it, when upon their Complaints which they make ſo much noiſe about, they fly to other places for Remedies, and not to the Courts of Judicature, which are alwayes open to receive all juſt Complaints, and the Company as lyable to be fued in thoſe Courts, as any private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But if it ſhould be granted, that the Companies Agents abroad may have in ſome particular Caſes varied from, or exceeded their Inſtructions from hence, and thereby ſome particular Perſons have been agrieved, Are the Company here therefore guilty of thoſe Excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings? Eſpecially ſince it hath been their conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that if any Perſons come from thence, who find themſelves agrieved by ſuch irregular Proceedings made in <hi>India,</hi> upon their Complaint made to the Company here, They do order the ſaid matter to be re-examined, and heard by ſome of their Members here, and if their Complaints be juſt, never fail to give the injured Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſatisfaction; as may be inſtanced in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: And it is irrational to affirm, that any Perſon can
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29900:6"/>be rendred Criminal by the Tranſactions of his Agents abroad, unleſs done upon his Order; for though in ſome particular Caſes, as they may be circumſtantiated, he may be lyable to make ſatisfaction, for Injuries done by his Agent abroad; yet Criminal no Man can ever be ſaid to be, but from Actions done by himſelf, or by his Order.</p>
            <p>To this it may be believed, Divers Perſons will reply, What! Is it denyed, that the Company have exceeded the Powers granted them in their Charters? How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it then to paſs, That the Right Honourable the Houſe of Commons have declared that their Proceedings at St. <hi>Helena</hi> were illegal? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For anſwer to which, It muſt firſt be declared, That it is not the buſineſs of this Paper, nor the intention of the Author of it, to diſpute, much leſs to determine the legality, or illegality of their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in general, or any ſeparate Clauſes of it in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: That being premiſed, this is certain, that they had Martial Law granted them in their Charter, and as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that their Predeceſſors had from time to time ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Commiſſions of that Nature, particularly in the Reigns of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt; the Originals of which lye yet by them: That they had in that very affair the particular Commiſſion and Orders from His then Majeſty; ſo that in that affair, how cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable ſoever to ſome they may ſeem to be, It was their Charter which had once been judicially affirmed in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> warranted by a particular Commiſſion from their then Soveraign as to that affair, that led them into the Error; Nor did, nor well could they know, until the Houſe of Commons had declared it, that ſuch proceedings were illegal; ſince their preſent Charter, and the then Kings particular Commiſſion, and the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and Uſages of their Predeceſſors, ſufficiently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by ſeveral Original Commiſſions of Martial Law lying by them, ſeemed to warrant them: So that though
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29900:6"/>their proceedings therein ſhould not be ſtrictly juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet are they fairly excuſable, becauſe led into the Error ignorantly; And that upon ſuch grounds as are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; and they being Merchants, and not Lawyers, the Illegality of it, was by them not eaſily to be diſcerned. And this fairly bringeth me to the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the next particular in this Objection, which is, To conſider how far this Company can be accounted Criminals, by Acting under the Powers of their preſent Charters, which ſome are pleaſed to affirm are not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, becauſe not made, or confirmed by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And here as before, Be it far from me to diſpute, much leſs determine the Legality or Illegality of their Charters in general, or any branches of it in particular; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a point beyond the intentions of this Diſcourſe, and no ways as is conceived, fit to be handled by a private Perſon. But how this preſent <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>-Company, over and above all Companies whatſoever, ſhould be eſteemed Criminal, by acting by the ſame Powers, and under the ſame Authority that all other Companies do, (One on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is the <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Company being excepted) is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy conſideration. It is well known, that upon the firſt Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade in this Nation, the Adventurers were eſtabliſhed in a Company with a Joynt Stock by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as by her Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, in the Forty Third Year of her Reign appeareth; That during the remainder of that Reign, they traded as a Company, excluſive to all others without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, under the Powers granted to them by the ſaid Charter. That by King <hi>James</hi> the firſt their Charter was again renewed, and they continued in the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Trade excluſive to Interlopers, by vertue of the ſame Powers during His Reign, and that of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt. True it is, That in the time of the late
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29900:7"/>Uſurpation, more particularly, from the year One Thouſand Six Hundred Fifty Three, to the year One Thouſand Six Hundred Fifty Seven; they were inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their Trade by Interlopers, ſo that in a manner the whole Trade was carryed on by private hands, and by that means the Trade of <hi>India</hi> was brought to that miſerable paſs, as it became ſo far from being an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous Trade, that to the knowledge and experience of many yet living, it proved the contrary; And while our Neighbours the <hi>Dutch</hi> managed the ſame Trade in a Company and Joynt Stock to their great advantage, The <hi>Engliſh</hi> by a general permiſſion to all Perſons to trade thither, drove on their Trade to a conſiderable loſs, beſides many indignities, affronts, and injuries, which were by ſeveral Princes in <hi>India</hi> where they traded put upon them; even to the forcing them to ſell their Goods, and to take others at ſuch Rates, and Price as they pleaſed; which could not have been put upon a Company in a Joynt Stock: This made the then Traders thither (though originally Interlopers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) to apply to the Uſurper <hi>Oliver</hi> for the Erecting a New <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, as He did in the Year 1657; and during his time, they enjoyed their Trade, <hi>excluſive</hi> to all Interlopers. Upon the happy Reſtauration of His late Majeſty, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, The Company applyed themſelves to Him, for the renewal of their Charter, and had it granted to them accordingly; And under the Powers thereof, enjoyed the Trade to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in all peaceable manner both here and in <hi>India, excluſive to all Interlopers,</hi> until about the Year 1680; About which time, and in the following Years, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being then in a ferment, they were broke in upon by Interlopers, their now inveterate Enemies: The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal conſequence of which, in relation to the Intereſt of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29900:7"/>the Nation, will be more particularly conſidered, when I come to diſcourſe of the <hi>Origine</hi> of the War in <hi>India.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Trade being as above broke in upon by Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopers, They did as in reaſon they ought, addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their then Soveraign, the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, for further Powers to obviate thoſe inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, who being fully convinced of the neceſſity of them, in order to the preſerving that Trade to the Nation, granted them accordingly, which were afterwards again renewed, and confirmed by the late King <hi>James</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>This being then the true ſtate of matter of Fact, as to the carrying on of the <hi>Trade</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> ever ſince it was eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> it is fairly left to the Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Judgment of all Indifferent and unprejudiced Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to judge, what the preſent Company could or ſhould have done, when their Trade was ſo broke in upon by Interlopers. Should they have broke up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and traded as private Perſons? That had been infallibly to have loſt the Trade to the Nation: Should they have continued their Trade in a Joynt Stock, and permitted all Freedom to the Interlopers? That had been as certain to have ruined themſelves firſt, and let the Trade be utterly loſt in time: Or, Should they (as ſome do alledge) have got their Charter to have been confirmed by Act of Parliament? That it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, had been as happy for them, as it was earneſtly deſired by them: But thoſe who ſhall ſeriouſly conſider, the temper of the Princes of the two laſt Reigns, how tender they were upon all the points of their Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, muſt withal acknowledge, that ſuch an attempt in them, would have been to have attempted that, which was next door to an impoſſibility: Should they have firſt addreſſed themſelves to the King for ſuch an Act of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29900:8"/>Confirmation, they would have been rejected with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, ſcorn and contempt, as calling in queſtion the validity of that Power derived from their Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; by which they had enjoyed the Trade all along ſince its firſt eſtabliſhment: Should they have petitioned the Parliament that then was, for an Act to eſtabliſh it? For <hi>that</hi> being to paſs the Royal Aſſent, would in all Mens Judgment (ſhould ſuch an Act have paſſed both Houſes) have been there rejected, and either of the late Kings ſo far exaſperated againſt the Company by an attempt of that Nature, in diminution of their Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that the leaſt which could have been expected, had been a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> upon their backs, to an utter diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of them; So that upon the whole matter, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Company were put upon this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> either to relinguiſh the Trade to the Interlopers, and trade as private Perſons, which had been as before hinted to ruine themſelves firſt, and loſe the Trade to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in time: Or to continue the Trade in a Joynt Stock <hi>excluſive</hi> to <hi>Interlopers,</hi> upon and under the ſame Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers they then had; as that Trade had been carryed on, ever ſince its firſt eſtabliſhment; Which they doing, How can it reaſonably be fixed upon them, that they were therefore Criminal, or any wayes deſerve thoſe black aſperſions, which are now caſt upon them for ſo doing? Which is all ſhall be ſaid to this laſt part of the firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: That they had acted upon the Powers in their Charter; which as ſome are pleaſed to ſay, are not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, as not confirmed by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>The next Objection againſt the preſent Company, by which they are endeavoured to be rendred vile and odious, is, that they are in a Bankrupt Condition; An Imaginary Fund, a Nominal Stock, not having any Eſtate or real Stock: And to fortifie this Calumny, they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29900:8"/>have been pleaſed to take the pains, to draw up the form of an account, wherein beſides vaſt Sums left in Blank, They have therein made the preſent Company to be 900000 <hi>l.</hi> worſe than nothing: A moſt excellent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt! and ſutable it is confeſſed to the confidence of the Undertaker. To enter upon the examination of any of the particulars therein contained, would ſeem as ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, as their attempt of expoſing them: Since no Man that underſtands any Dealing in the World, but underſtandeth withal, that at that rate, it is an eaſie matter, to make any, either Community, or Private Perſons Bankrupt at their pleaſure. Sufficient it is, that the preſent Company are not only willing, but able to pay their own juſt Debts, without being liable to ſatisfie the capricious Demands of every idle Brain: Nor can any one be ſaid to be in a Bankrupt Condition, who neither hideth his Head, nor refuſeth Payments of his Juſt Debts when due; neither of which is done by the preſent Company. How far their Enemies have prevailed to render them (if poſſible) what they would fain have them, and give them out to be; may appear, by the Companies having been required to give a true ſtate of their Stock, by delivering in a perfect Account of their Moneys, Goods, and Debts both here and in <hi>India,</hi> as they now ſtand in their Books: A thing juſtly queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, Whether ever before demanded, of either private Perſon, or Commonalty; Since expoſing themſelves and their whole concern to ſo publick a view, muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have broke them, had they not had a valuable and real Stock to have ſubſiſted upon: Notwithſtanding which, the Company did humbly ſubmit to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and in Obedience to it, did preſent to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee of Parliament, a Faithful, Juſt and True account of the ſame, and perfect ſo far as their Books did enable them: And to make their candidneſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29900:9"/>therein appear, For the Juſtification of the ſaid Accompt, did humbly ſubmit the inſpection of their Books, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Valuation of their Stock, to ſuch Committee as the Honourable the Houſe of Commons ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, and their laſt Advices from <hi>India</hi> to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Chairman of the ſaid Committee, or to ſuch two or three of them, as the Committee ſhould appoint; not thinking it reaſonable, that their whole concerns ſhould be expoſed to the publick view, whereby their inveterate Enemies would likewiſe have come to the knowledge of them. And that not without reaſon, ſince a Copy of that very individual Account, which was by the Company preſented to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, was immediately by ſome of their Adverſaries ſent into <hi>Holland,</hi> for them to make ſuch advantages of it, to the prejudice of the Company, as they ſhould think fit; as may appear by a Tranſcript of it, return'd to ſome <hi>Jews</hi> here, with a deſire to be inform'd by them, Whether that Tranſcript agreed with the Account de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in by the Company. So that what uſes they would have made of ſuch an advantage, is eaſily judged by thoſe who ſhall conſider what they have done without it. But to cloſe this Subject, which is ſo apparent a Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that it may rationally be ſuppoſed, they themſelves do not believe, what they do ſo induſtriouſly inſinuate into the belief of others. For whenever was any Man envied that was worſe than nothing? Or to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is the diſſolution of the preſent Company ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired by them, if they are worſe than nothing, and are not able to carry on their Trade; For if that be true, they will quickly diſſolve in courſe, nor will their Credit be able long to ſupport them, without there be a <hi>real</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial Stock</hi> left to found it upon; That having been as much blaſted, as the Wit or Malice of Men could invent. Divers other publick Funds have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29900:9"/>failed, The Exchequer that hath been ſtopped, The Chamber of <hi>London</hi> that hath not been able to comply; The moſt noted Bankers have turned Bankrupt, and ſome other Companies there are, which ſhall be here nameleſs, whoſe Debts are now of a long ſtanding, and are not yet ſatisfied: But where is the Perſon that ever lent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to this <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>-Company, which have not been ſatisfied both their <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Intereſt?</hi> their greateſt Enemies cannot inſtance in any one ſingle Perſon. And ſhall thoſe who have ſo faithfully and readily complyed with all their Engagements, be now upon the bare affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their Enemies eſteemed Bankrupt, until they are guilty of ſome Action, that may truly render them ſuch? No, no! It is not their Poverty, but their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Wealth, that hath created them ſo many Enemies, amongſt which (more ungrateful they) are ſome, who have been <hi>Servants</hi> under them, and have taken the <hi>Oath of a Freeman,</hi> of the ſaid Company, or purely raiſed by them. True it is, upon what Stock hath been continued there for divers years, or thoſe Perſons who have had the good Fortune to ſell themſelves out, when the Actions were very high (amongſt which are ſome of their now greateſt Enemies) Thoſe it is confeſſed, have made conſiderable advantage by it: But as for many, if not moſt of the preſent Adventurers, who came in when the Stock was ſold very high, they will be ſo far from deſerving Envy, that they will rather deſerve Pity; (amongſt which are many Widows and Orphans) in as much as they will be moſt certainly great ſufferers by a Diſſolution. Notwithſtanding which, the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany have not preſumed like their Adverſaries to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate to the Legiſlative Power of the Nation, the very terms of the Act to be by them paſſed: But as in Duty bound, in their Petition lodg'd with the Chairman of the Committee, in order to be preſented to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29900:10"/>Houſe of Commons, did ſubmit themſelves and their Concerns to the Juſtice and Wiſdom of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Another Aſperſion, which is caſt upon the preſent Company, and urged by their Adverſaries, as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for their diſſolution, is, That its preſent Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution is not ſufficiently National: To which is anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That what is free for every Man to come into, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be <hi>limited.</hi> It is well known, that by the preſent Conſtitution, no Man is debarred coming into it, either Engliſhman or Stranger: It is likewiſe well known, That there is every day Stock to be bought on the Exchange (and that much cheaper, if Truth may be the Judge, then it is really worth) ſo that no Man but may when he pleaſeth come into the Company, and have what ſhare in the Trade he pleaſeth, ſo far as he is able to purchaſe. And what greater extent can any new Company to be Erected, have than this, where no Man is debarred?</p>
            <p>But whereas they further Object,</p>
            <p>That the preſent Stock is not ſufficient to carry on ſo great a Trade, as thoſe Places comprized within their Priviledge will bear. It is anſwered, Suppoſe that to be true, which is not granted; yet that defect may be ſupplyed otherwiſe than by a diſſolution, even by an enlargement of Stock in a new additional Subſcription, to ſuch an increaſe, as the Wiſdom of the Nation ſhall think fit; Nor need they fear to graft their new Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription upon the preſent Stock, notwithſtanding thoſe Twelve Reaſons inſtanced in their late ſcurrilous Paper, (which had they been penned without ſuch opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Expreſſions, ſhould have received an Anſwer; but being ſuch as they are, put out not to convince others, but to blaſt the Company, they deſerve none) For in truth, Whatever the Adverſaries of the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany do, or may exclaim to the contrary, their preſent Stock is really worth more, than it was then valued at,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29900:10"/>and will and muſt appear ſo, when Perſons indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen on both ſides, ſhall examine it; in order to the adjuſting of its Valuation.</p>
            <p>But if it be further alledged, that there are many of the Conſtitutions of the preſent Company, which render it not ſo comprehenſively National, as otherwiſe it might be; As the great quantity of the <hi>Stock</hi> in the hands of ſome particular Perſons, and conſequently the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage they may have thereby, by the Number of their Votes, as to the management of it. It is anſwered, Not to enter upon particulars: Divers of theſe things are ſubmitted by them, to the Regulation of the Wiſdom of the Parliament, as appeareth by the Scheme by them delivered into the Honourable the Committee of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, at their Command: And this is all ſhall be ſaid as to this Objection.</p>
            <p>Another thing that the Adverſaries of the preſent Company do take advantage to calumniate them upon, is the preſent <hi>War</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> which they endeavour to make the World believe, was entred into them by capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, and not enforced thereunto by the Neceſſity of Affairs; Whereas the contraty is true, that they were not only neceſſitated thereunto, But that the Occaſion of that Neceſſity did ariſe from the breaking in of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlopers upon them into their Trade (which are now the greateſt Exclaimers againſt the War) which break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon them by the ſaid Interlopers, and thereby the dividing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in <hi>India,</hi> The Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did wiſely foreſee would inevitably occaſion, either the breach of all the <hi>Agreements</hi> made by their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors and themſelves, with the great <hi>Mogul,</hi> by and under which, they had enjoyed their Trade with all peaceableneſs and quietneſs from its firſt Eſtabliſhment, to that time; and that thereby they would be enforced tamely to ſubmit unto all ſuch <hi>Impoſitions</hi> and <hi>Avenia</hi>'s
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29900:11"/>which his <hi>Avaritious Officers</hi> would at their pleaſure lay upon them, and raiſe out of their Eſtates, Or they muſt be at the <hi>charge,</hi> and run the hazard of a <hi>War,</hi> to oblige the <hi>Moors</hi> to make good their former <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>Phirmaunds:</hi> One of theſe two was certainly foreſeen, would follow the dividing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt as above, and accordingly the Company did prepare for the worſt: Notwithſtanding which, they did not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any Hoſtile Act (though they had reaſon enough to have begun, having had very great Sums of Money extorted from them,) until the <hi>Moors</hi> by their barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Murder of an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> and aſſaulting the reſt at <hi>Hughly</hi> begun the War, and became the Agreſſors, which will moſt plainly appear, by giving a true, though ſhort Account of the <hi>Origine</hi> of the War, which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>It is well known, What a flouriſhing Condition the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>-Company were in about the Years 1680, 1681, 1682, 1683. When beſides many large Dividents to the Adventurers, their <hi>ſingle Stock</hi> was ſold for 360 <hi>per Cent.</hi> to the admiration of Foreigners, and Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own Countreymen; eſpecially ſome Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who made not the like advantage in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Trades; who though they might have come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Company, and enjoyed a ſhare of the Trade with them; Yet reſolving to go a ſhorter way to work, and taking advantage of the great fermentation that was then in this Nation, ariſing between ſeveral different Parties, and Perſwaſions of Men; they fell to <hi>Interloping,</hi> into which, many well-meaning Men, by the Craft of ſome Cunning deſigning Perſons (bred in the ſaid Companies Service,) and the hopes of finding quicker returns for their Stock, by an Interloping Trade, than they could do, by coming into the Companies Stock, gave them the encouragement. And this proceeded ſo far, as to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29900:11"/>ſending out for <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> at ſeveral times, very many private Ships, with large Stocks, contrary to the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Charter, and His then Majeſties Proclamation. Upon the whole, the Company did addreſs themſelves to His then Majeſty, humbly repreſenting unto him the Injuſtice of ſuch Proceedings, and the deſtructive con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences to the Company, to whom the ſole Trade had been granted by his ſaid Majeſty <hi>excluſive</hi> to all others: By which they had been encouraged to be at vaſt charges in the Eſtabliſhment of it, and were at ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Expences in maintaining Forts and Garriſons to defend it: And withal, did further repreſent to His ſaid Majeſty, what evil conſequences ſuch attempts would have upon the Trade and Navigation of this Kingdom, by ſuch a diviſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt and Nation in <hi>India;</hi> particularly, that it would be a means to looſe all the <hi>Engliſh Priviledges</hi> in <hi>India;</hi> That the Native Governours of <hi>India</hi> would oppreſs the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſeeing them ſo divided, And the <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Danes</hi> would make their advantages of ſuch a confuſion amongſt the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Their Debtors in <hi>India</hi> would neglect to pay them their juſt Debts, And above all, All the Wicked and Evil diſpoſed Perſons amongſt the Companies Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, Factors and Servants, would, that they might the better carry on their deſigns of wronging the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and enriching themſelves, joyn themſelves to the ſaid Interlopers, which if not prevented, would produce <hi>Rebellion</hi> in ſome of the Companies Garriſons in <hi>India;</hi> So that the loſs and expence of a Million of Money, and many <hi>Engliſh</hi> mens Lives, would not re-eſtate the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in <hi>India,</hi> in ſo proſperous a condition, as it was before the breaking in of the ſaid Interlopers into their Trade: All which they humbly ſubmitted to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties conſideration, nor were they out in their Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures; For accordingly as they did foreſee, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29900:12"/>to His Majeſty, in their repreſentations to him, it came to paſs; For upon the firſt arrival of the Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in <hi>India,</hi> They to procure Abettors to themſelves, and the better to carry on their own Undertakings, corrupted ſome of the Companies old Servants, which had lived long abroad; gave out many untruths of the Companyes weak condition in <hi>Europe;</hi> Suggeſted that the old Company were fallen under the diſpleaſure of the King; That the Nation was under great diſturbances; That themſelves were the new Company: All which untrue reports were ecchoed and improved by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the preſent Company; eſpecially, by ſuch of their Servants, as by their unfaithful dealings, had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred themſelves obnoxious, and conſequently had no way ſo proper to ſecure themſelves, as to herd and joyn with the Interlopers: Upon this, Captain <hi>Kegwin,</hi> with other Confederates, ſet up for themſelves; at <hi>Bombay;</hi> and under pretence, that our Nation was together by the Ears, and that the Company was in Rebellion againſt His Majeſty, They declared for the King exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to the Company, Impriſoned the Companies Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Governour there, refuſed Obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Preſident; Seized on the Companies Treaſure, and took the Companies own Ships, Arming and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them againſt the Company, particularly the <hi>Hunter</hi> and <hi>Return,</hi> and ſome other ſmaller Ships. And our <hi>Rivals in Trade</hi> took the advantage of dividing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in <hi>India,</hi> which was not to be let ſlip, to poſſeſs themſelves of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and drove the <hi>Engliſh</hi> from thence.</p>
            <p>The like conſequences upon the Report and Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Interlopers, followed at St. <hi>Helena,</hi> where almoſt the whole Iſland ran into an open Rebellion, and attempted to take the Companies Caſtle by force of Arms; and by imitation of the Rebels at <hi>Bombay,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the King; Set up the Union Flag, and with Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29900:12"/>flying aſſaulted the Fort,) But by Gods good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence were prevented; For had they ſucceeded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, not being able to maintain it themſelves without ſupport from <hi>England,</hi> they muſt and would have <hi>ſold</hi> it to Foreigners, and run away with the Moneys to have ſecured themſelves.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Bengal,</hi> where the Companies Chief Trade was, the <hi>Nabob</hi> or Governour, and thoſe under him, took the advantage of thoſe Reports, and the dividing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in <hi>India,</hi> to break all their agreements formerly made with the Company, and their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and deprive them of all thoſe very great Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had ſo long enjoyed under former ſtipulations; drew great ſums of Money from both Parties, by ſuch oppreſſive wayes of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Injuſtice, and open Hoſtility; as at another time, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were united under the prudent Conduct of the Company, would not have been, nor never was before attempted; Which they were encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to do, becauſe the Interlopers, that they might carry on their Trade, ſubmitted to any Impoſitions the <hi>Moors</hi> would lay upon them, though never ſo much more than the Company by their Agreements were bound to pay.</p>
            <p>The particulars of the Injuries ſuſtained, and of the ſeveral Sums of Money extorted from them, as they were then faithfully repreſented by them, to His then Majeſty and Council, are too long here to incert: But ſuch as they were, as together with the apprehenſion of looſing the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in <hi>India,</hi> did ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with His Majeſty, as to conſider what proper <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies</hi> to apply to ſuch an inevitable Miſchief, and made uſe of theſe two; The one, the preventing the further <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>Interlopers</hi> which had been the root of all the Miſchiefs; which He did by iſſuing out his Proclamation to reſtrain them, and order all the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29900:13"/>Nation</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> either to come home, or put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the ſervice of the Company, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt might not be divided, but <hi>united</hi> in one: And further, in order to the preventing ſo great a Miſchief, and the better to countenance the Company in their proceedings, He ſent one of his own Ships of <hi>War</hi> into <hi>India,</hi> with <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to ſieze upon all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that he could meet withal there.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Injuries,</hi> the Company ſuſtained, by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives taking away all their <hi>Priviledges,</hi> though never ſo firmly ſtipulated by former agreements (which certainly being once gone, could never be again recovered by Complements) and exacting from them ſeveral great Sums of Money: The <hi>Remedy</hi> pitched upon by His then Majeſty, was by directing the Company to put themſelves in a poſture to right themſelves, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the like for the future; and to that end, granted them ſuch <hi>new Powers,</hi> as were neceſſary for the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on ſo great a work, as appeareth by the <hi>ſupplements</hi> to their <hi>Charter, viz.</hi> The Erecting of Courts of <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty</hi> in <hi>India</hi> in ſeveral places, and empowering all the Companies Ships, with <hi>Commiſſions of War,</hi> from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who alſo had particular Power, Order, and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from His ſaid Majeſty, to ſeize all <hi>Interlopers</hi> in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and compel them by force of Arms, in caſe of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to go up to ſuch places, where the Company had their Reſidence and Garriſons, that ſo the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt might be no longer <hi>divided,</hi> which had been the Root of all the Miſchief, to the hazzard of the loſs of the whole Trade.</p>
            <p>Purſuant to whoſe Direction, and empowered by the Authority of their ſaid Soveraign, (which might very well be by them thought ſufficient for their Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it being never yet queſtion'd, but that the <hi>Power</hi> of making <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> was veſted in the Crown.)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29900:13"/>The Company were at very great charges, in ſending out divers great <hi>Ships</hi> fitted with all manner of Warlike Proviſions, furniſhed with Land-Soldiers, in order firſt to reduce their own Factories of <hi>Bombay</hi> and St. <hi>Helena,</hi> which were then in Rebellion; And afterwards by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing ſo formidable, it might the better incline the <hi>Moors</hi> to come to an amicable agreement, with them, by reſtoring them their former Priviledges, which they had ſo unjuſtly deprived them of, and give them ſome ſatisfaction, for thoſe Extortions they had exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; which they were to endeavour firſt by all <hi>fair means</hi> imaginable.</p>
            <p>According to which, the Iſlands of <hi>Bombay,</hi> and St. <hi>Helena</hi> were reduced; and ſetled under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Company: Some of the Interlopers ſeized on by His Majeſties Ship the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> Captain <hi>Tyrrel</hi> Commander. The Kings Proclamation iſſued out, and proclaimed for all <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> to withdraw themſelves out of the Service of Foreign Princes, and to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Companies Garriſons and Reſidences, that ſo the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt might no more be divided, and all ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable means made uſe of, to come to a juſt agreement with the Natives: Nor was there by the Company any Hoſtile Act committed (though thereunto ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, by many great and repeated injuries) until the buſineſs which hapned at <hi>Hughly,</hi> wherein the <hi>Moors</hi> were the <hi>Agreſſors,</hi> as doth appear by a particular Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of the ſaid Action, extracted out of the Companies Letter, how that begun, <hi>which is as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">The <hi>28th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1686, At <hi>Hughly,</hi> in the Bay of <hi>Bengal,</hi> Three of the Companies Souldiers going into the <hi>Buzar,</hi> or Market place as uſual, to purchaſe Victuals in the Morning, were not only denyed the ſame, but were violently ſet upon by the Governours Peons or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29900:14"/>Souldiers, were ſorely beat and cut (of which, one of them dyed of his wounds then received,) then bound, and carryed Priſoners to <hi>Abdul Gunny,</hi> the Governour of the place: The News of which, immediately arrived at the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factory, in the ſaid Town of <hi>Hughly,</hi> in theſe <hi>terms,</hi> That two <hi>Engliſh</hi> men were ſet upon by the Governours, Peons, or Souldiers, and were deſperately cut and <hi>wounded,</hi> and lay a <hi>dying</hi> in the Highway, Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Captain <hi>Leſhly</hi> was immediately ordered out with a Party, with Orders to bring in their Bodies dead or alive; but to offer <hi>violence</hi> to no Man, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they were aſſaulted; Which they attempting to do, were upon the way, ſet upon by a Body of Horſe and Foot, in a Hoſtile manner, whom they received, as Men not willing to be wanting in their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and after ſome skirmiſh, put them to flight; having in the Engagement killed and wounded ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them: The whole Town being immediately upon this alarm'd, ſet fire to thoſe of their own Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which were neareſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factory, by which many of the Companies Goods were conſumed.</q> What followeth in the ſaid Narrative, is but a further proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of repeated Acts of <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Hoſtility, each</hi> againſt the <hi>other;</hi> And it being not the intent of this Diſcourſe, to give you a full <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>War,</hi> (which poſſibly hereafter may be done by another hand) and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in it, but only the true occaſions of the <hi>Riſe</hi> of it, I thought it needleſs to carry it on further; ſo much of it as is here inſerted, being ſufficient to give you a true account how it began, Whereby it appeareth. That the <hi>Moors</hi> were the firſt <hi>Aggreſſors,</hi> and the firſt Blood ſhed in this War, was by them.</p>
            <p>Thus having in as contracted a manner as I could, give you an account of the <hi>Origine</hi> of the War: Which I do aſſure the Reader, is done with all faithfulneſs and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29900:14"/>truth, ſo far as I was enabled, by all the Light I could gather out of the Companies <hi>Records;</hi> either as to their Proceedings here, or their advices from <hi>India:</hi> I do ſubmit the whole to your peruſal and Judgment, and do appeal to the reaſon of every impartial Man, whither upon the ſame, theſe following <hi>particulars</hi> are not plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, rightly, and truly to be inferred.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Company did for many years, from its Eſtabliſhment, until about the Year 1680, enjoy their Trade, by vertue of their <hi>Charters</hi> at home, and their <hi>agreements</hi> with the <hi>Indians</hi> abroad, without any moleſtation, and with all Peace and good agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the Perſons with whom they traded.</p>
            <p>That the ſaid Company were now neceſſitated to defend themſelves by <hi>Arms,</hi> from the many <hi>Injuries</hi> dayly done unto them, and to endeavour thereby the regaining of thoſe <hi>Priviledges,</hi> which both they, and their Predeceſſors had ſo long enjoyed, by vertue of formal Stipulations and Agreements, ſolemnly made and agreed to, between the <hi>Indians</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the ſole occaſion of the depriving them of their Priviledges, and putting ſuch exactions upon them, by the <hi>Indians,</hi> and conſequently of the <hi>War</hi> for <hi>regaining</hi> them, was the <hi>Interlopers</hi> breaking in upon them in their Trade, thereby dividing the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Intereſt</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> which rendred them contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the eſteem of the Natives, and incouraged them to do them thoſe Injuries; ſo that ſome of <hi>thoſe Perſons,</hi> who now ſo much exclaim againſt that War, were the ſole occaſion of it.</p>
            <p>That the Encouragements, the Companies Servants received from the Interlopers, and the advantages they made by joyning with them, was the ſole occaſion of the two <hi>Rebellions</hi> in the Iſlands of <hi>Bombay,</hi> and St.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29900:15"/>
               <hi>Helena,</hi> and conſequently of the vaſt charge the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was at, and the bloodſhed that was ſpilt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining of them.</p>
            <p>That the Company being ſo put upon a neceſſity of defending and righting themſelves by Arms, did not do it unadviſedly, but did in all humility <hi>addreſs</hi> themſelves to their then Soveraign, in whoſe Perſon it was alwayes believed the right of making <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> was veſted, and took not only his Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but his Directions and Authority therein, teſtified by the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> for the War, and granting <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of War</hi> to all the Captains, which went out in the Companies Service, and ſending one of His Royal Ships in that Service.</p>
            <p>That notwithſtanding the many <hi>Injuries</hi> received by the Company, the <hi>exacting</hi> and <hi>taking away</hi> from them ſeveral great Sums of <hi>Money,</hi> and breaking their ſolemn <hi>agreements</hi> made by them, with the preſent Company, and their Predeceſſors, in depriving them of their <hi>Priviledges</hi> enjoyed ſo long time by vertue of the ſaid agreements: The Company did commit no Act of <hi>Hoſtility,</hi> until the <hi>Indians</hi> had made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>Agreſſors</hi> in ſhedding the firſt Bloodſhed in this War, in the buſineſs of <hi>Hughly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The foregoing particulars being ſo clearly and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally to be inferred, from the true account which hath been given above of the <hi>Riſe</hi> of the <hi>War,</hi> I ſhall only add, the great and many Endeavours, and Attempts, which the Company hath made, ſince the firſt Eruption of the War, to the attainment of a wiſhed for <hi>Peace,</hi> That ſo it may appear, That as the Company were by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and not willingly engaged in the ſaid War, ſo they are moſt willing and deſirous of a Peace; as is evident, by the ſeveral attempts they have made thereunto: As
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29900:15"/>firſt, After the unhappy Eruption at <hi>Hughly,</hi> there was made a ceſſation of Arms, in order to an <hi>accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> but it proved ineffectual through the deceitfulneſs of the <hi>Moors;</hi> After that, in the ſaid Bay of <hi>Bengala,</hi> there was a <hi>perfect Peace</hi> made between the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the <hi>Moors;</hi> The particular <hi>Articles</hi> thereof being in number Twelve, were ſent to the Company; But the <hi>Moors</hi> as ſoon as they had attained their ends upon the Company, in getting them to quit their Fort, they moſt perfidiouſly receded from their agreements, and broke it.</p>
            <p>Since that, There hath been made two ſeveral <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements</hi> with the <hi>Nabob,</hi> or Governour of <hi>Surrat;</hi> and an aſſurance by him of the great <hi>Mogul</hi>'s ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; But when the Council at <hi>Surrat,</hi> upon Summons, came to receive the <hi>Mogul</hi>'s <hi>Ratification,</hi> according to the ſaid <hi>Agreement,</hi> they were made Priſoners, and at the ſame time, A Detachement of Horſe and Foot ſent to ſurpriſe the General and Council at <hi>Swally:</hi> And much about the ſame time, Another Army ſent to ſurprize <hi>Bombay,</hi> which they apprehended, might eaſily be done in the Generals abſence. So that it was no ſham upon the Nation, as by ſome is ſuggeſted, for the Company to give out, that the Peace was made in <hi>India;</hi> for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Advices they received from thence, which they muſt govern themſelves by, <hi>It</hi> was really made, and on account of the very <hi>Articles</hi> upon which it was made, was ſent to them: But who could foreſee, that the <hi>Moors</hi> would make no other uſe of thoſe Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than thereby to make the General more ſecure, and leſs mindful; while in the mean time, in a moſt treacherous manner, they plotted his deſtruction; And when their Plots had not taken thoſe Effects they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, they moſt perfidiouſly fell from their Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>When the laſt Letters came from <hi>Bombay,</hi> which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29900:16"/>bore date the <hi>9th,</hi> and <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1689. The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral had again condeſcended to a <hi>Ceſſation of Arms,</hi> in order to a <hi>Peace,</hi> which he would with all his Induſtry endeavour to obtain, and was the better in hopes of it, by reaſon of an Information, he had juſt then received from one <hi>Sheck Ebraim,</hi> that he was coming to him with a Letter, directed to him from the great <hi>Mogul</hi> himſelf, (a reſpect with them moſt extraordinary) but whether they will be more real in this Treaty, than they were in the former, or only as then, pretend an inclination to Peace with the General, that they may the better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him by War: Time, and our next Advices from thence muſt diſcover. This is true, That in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and under a Ceſſation of Arms, in order to an Accommodation, things ſtood when our <hi>laſt Advices</hi> came from thence, which I pray God may anſwer the Companies Expectation in a firm and good Peace: For certainly it cannot be ſuppoſed, much leſs believed, even by their Adverſaries themſelves; That the Company ſhould in the leaſt deſire the continuance of the War, and not be willing to make all poſſible Condeſcentions, for the obtaining a Peace; Since no one can receive more <hi>prejudice</hi> by the War, nor none reap <hi>greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> by the Peace, than the preſent Company: (and Intereſt, you know, will not lie.) Though the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries of the Company do make uſe of this amongſt other their Calumnies, That the Company do needleſly continue the War, and not uſe their endeavours for the obtaining of a Peace, and yet, at the ſame time, by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing to the World, in the <hi>Preamble</hi> to their <hi>new Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions,</hi> that the Company ſhould be obliged by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> to <hi>purchaſe</hi> a <hi>Peace,</hi> have done as much as in them lyeth, to render it next door to an impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ever to obtain it; which will come to be conſider'd, amongſt thoſe <hi>Obſervations,</hi> which ſhall be made upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29900:16"/>ſome of the particulars of the ſaid <hi>Preamble:</hi> And this is what at preſent I think ſufficient to anſwer to that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, ſo induſtriouſly ſpread abroad by the Enemies of the preſent Company, that They did begin the War in <hi>India,</hi> not out of neceſſity, but capriciouſly; and have, and do continue it wilfully.</p>
            <p>Having thus (as briefly as I well could) anſwered the main and moſt plauſible Objections againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, by which their Adverſaries endeavoured to render them ſo odious to the World, It may not be amiſs in the cloſe of this Diſcourſe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider a little, the <hi>Preamble</hi> to their <hi>new Subſcription,</hi> by them lately Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Not to enlarge upon the boldneſs of the Attempt in General, which hath been hinted at already: As for <hi>them</hi> to <hi>Erect,</hi> as it were <hi>a new Company,</hi> before ever the matter was come into either of the <hi>Two Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> Or, That any of them had voted, <hi>There ſhould be one:</hi> And, Not only ſo, but to take upon them to dictate to the whole Legiſlative Power of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, King, Lord,</hi> and <hi>Commons, the very terms of an Act to be by them paſſed,</hi> (or elſe their Subſcriptions ſignifie nothing:) Which is as much as to ſay, If we may have a new Company upon our <hi>own Terms,</hi> we will; but if not, we will have <hi>none:</hi> And that which is yet a further degree of preſumption, they do publiſh to the World. <hi>That they have received aſſurance, That ſuch an Act ſhall be paſſed, even before the things are come into the Houſe of Commons,</hi> by a <hi>report</hi> from their <hi>own Committee.</hi> To come to the <hi>Preamble</hi> it ſelf: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in may be taken notice of the diſingenuity of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> and the <hi>unreaſonableneſs</hi> of the <hi>Terms</hi> by them preſcribed to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> For ſhould the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comply with the <hi>Terms</hi> by them <hi>propoſed,</hi> or <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed</hi> rather, It would be ſo far from promoting the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29900:17"/>Peace they ſeem ſo much to deſire, as that it would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly obſtruct it. In the <hi>Preface,</hi> they are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>That the Committee of the Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, did declare their Opinion, That the beſt way of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Trade, is, by a new Company, with a new Joynt Stock to be Eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament.</hi> And it is ſo for Truth, but it is not the whole Truth; For they moſt diſingeniouſly, leave out the latter part of the ſaid Vote, (which is, <hi>That the preſent Company be continued excluſive to Interlopers, and all Permiſſive Ships, until the ſaid Act of Parliament be paſſed,</hi>) as not for their Turn, and wholly inconſiſtent with their preſent Undertaking; for it being <hi>in Terminis, that the preſent Company ſhould be continued until the ſaid Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was paſſed,</hi> it doth wholly exclude the Erecting of a New Company until that be done. And what is the <hi>publiſhing</hi> their <hi>Preamble,</hi> conſiſting amongſt other things, of the Term of their preſent Conſtitution, and future Government of their new Company, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing when, and how their Governour and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees ſhould be Elected; their ſubſcribing ſeveral Sums of Moneys, and appointing when, and how their Subſcriptions ſhould be paid in, and propounding Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to ſuch, as ſhall timely pay in their Money; I ſay, What is all this, but as much as in them lieth, the <hi>Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting a new Company,</hi> during the continuance of the Old; and conſequently contrary to the Vote of the ſaid Committees; ſo that in ſtead of waiting the Iſſue of the Parliaments Determination: They by way of preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Erect their New Company to the deſtruction of the Old, which is quite contrary to the ſenſe of the Vote of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs,</hi> if not <hi>Injuſtice</hi> of their <hi>Terms</hi> hereby appear, in that they do require the Parliament to oblige by an Act, the preſent Company to make good
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29900:17"/>the demands of the Subjects of the great <hi>Mogul,</hi> and King of <hi>Syam,</hi> before it be ſo much as enquir'd into, much leſs known, of what Nature the ſaid demands are, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Debts contracted for Goods bought, or Goods taken by the Company <hi>Flagrante Bello,</hi> by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſal, for the Goods of the Company by them ſeized in the Companies Factories: But taking it for granted, without any Examination of matter of Fact, that this preſent Company have bin the <hi>Agreſſors;</hi> they would have by Act of Parliament, the Company be obliged to make good, whatever the Subjects of either of theſe two Princes ſhould demand. If they do reply, they do limit it to Debts and Demands that are juſt: In that caſe, I would deſire to be informed, Who ſhould adjuſt the Account? Should the Subjects of the Great <hi>Mogul,</hi> and King of <hi>Syam?</hi> it may be preſumed, That they would demand enough; eſpecially knowing before hand (as without doubt they would be well inform'd) that the Company are under an Obligation by Act of Parliament, to comply with their Demands. Or ſhould the preſent Company adjuſt the Account? that on the other hand would be thought to be done partially for themſelves. Or, Should the Account be ſtated and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted by Commiſſioners choſen reſpectively by the ſaid Princes and the Company? How can that well be, when there is no room left for ſuch an indifferent adjuſtment? that Act being once paſſed: For how can it be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there can be an equitable Arbitrament, where the one Party is at liberty to demand what they pleaſe, and the other Party previouſly bound up to comply with their Demands: Or, Should the New Company depute Perſons to adjuſt the ſaid Demands? it may reaſonably be ſuppoſed in that caſe, That thoſe who without cauſe, have ſo induſtriouſly endeavoured the ruin of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Company, in a matter of that Nature, will not be very favourable to their juſt Intereſt.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29900:18"/>
            <p>Nor is it leſs unjuſt, That they fix the <hi>Dammage</hi> (if any ſuch ſhould be due from the Company) as they do, to be made good by the <hi>Perſons,</hi> and out of the <hi>Eſtate</hi> of the <hi>Managers</hi> thereof: Whereas, It is well known to every one that knoweth any thing of the Company, that the Company being a Joynt Stock, and the Court of Committees, who are the Managers thereof; being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally many of them, as much if not more concerned in the Joynt Stock than others, are <hi>annually</hi> choſen by the Generalty; and by them intruſted with the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof, are not lyable, either in Law or Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in their own Perſons and Eſtates, to any Action for any thing done by them in the management of that their Truſt; For if they were, it is not reaſonable to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that any one would take upon him ſuch an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, where the Hazzard of any Miſcarriage ſhould be his; and the profit ariſing by ſuch ſucceſs, ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to the Joynt Stock. Beſides the Court of Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees conſiſteth of divers Men, choſen ſome one year, and ſome another; ſo that after that rate, thoſe who came in one year, may thereby be anſwerable for the miſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of thoſe, who were in before; a thing altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unjuſt and unreaſonable: Nor is it to be ſuppoſed, that thoſe who are the <hi>Erecters</hi> of this <hi>new Joynt Stock,</hi> would themſelves think this reaſonable to be one of the terms of its Conſtitution: <hi>That their Committees choſen for its management, ſhould be lyable in their own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates, to anſwer for all Miſcarriages which ſhould accrue to it, during the time of their being of the ſame;</hi> For if they had, they whould have certainly put it in, as as one of their <hi>terms</hi> in their Preamble, which they have no ways done.</p>
            <p>The next thing obſervable in their Preamble is, That they would have the Parliament to enact, <hi>That the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Stock ſhould defray the Charge of making Peace
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29900:18"/>with the ſaid</hi> Indian <hi>Princes:</hi> And certain it is, That no one who ever deſired Peace in <hi>India,</hi> as they ſeem to pretend to, took ſuch a prepoſterous way to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of it: Can it otherwiſe be believed. Then that thoſe <hi>Indian</hi> Princes (if they ſhould once come to the Knowledge, of ſuch an Obligation laid upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to buy their Peace with them,) would ſet a vaſt Price upon it? They are little acquainted with <hi>India,</hi> and the <hi>avaritious temper</hi> of their Princes in general, that think otherwayes. And the preſent Stock, and their new Stock added to it, would not be able to buy a Peace with them; they knowing (as certainly they would even by the Information, of ſome of the new Company,) that the Company were previouſly obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to purchaſe it of them; nor could they have taken a more certain way to prevent it, than they have done by publiſhing ſuch a Propoſition to the World: And it is to be wiſhed, That the publiſhing ſuch a Notion, though it never take effect, do not become a great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the making of it, or if already made, be not an encouragement to the <hi>Moors</hi> to break it.</p>
            <p>It is certain, Thta no Perſons have greater reaſon to deſire a Peace in <hi>India,</hi>) as whoſe Intereſt doth more lead them to it,) than the preſent Company: And it is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That they will do what becometh Prudent Men and Perſons ſo much concern'd for the attainment of it, even to the parting with much of their right: But the quickeſt and moſt effectual way for the obtaining ſuch a Bleſſing, is, That the preſent Company be ſupported, and not diſcountenanced by the preſent Government; for without that, all their Endeavours will prove ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual.</p>
            <p>What remaineth in the Preamble, relateth more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to their own New Eſtabliſhment; in which, Tho' many things may juſtly be objected againſt, yet not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29900:19"/>concerning the preſent Company, cometh not within the intention of this Diſcourſe; Only the deſign of their whole Project, by its ſeveral Circumſtances, may clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear to all ſuch, as ſhall but ſeriouſly conſider it, to be, to oblige the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as much as in them lay, by the <hi>Encouragement</hi> of a <hi>New Subſcription</hi> to <hi>deſtroy the preſent Company,</hi> otherwayes their Subſcriptions would not have bin ſo conditionally annexed to <hi>Terms;</hi> which they themſelves could not expect, That the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Juſtice of the Nation aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would ever aſſent to: And ſo at the ſame time, they hoped to attain their End; which was to to preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the preſent Company, without running any Haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of parting with their Money: But the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany have other <hi>Thoughts</hi> of the Wiſdom of the Nation, aſſembled in Parliament: And as they have, ſo they will alwayes be ready to <hi>ſubmit themſelves to the Wiſdom and Juſtice of that</hi> Auguſt Aſſembly; not doubting, but when <hi>they</hi> come to weigh things ſeriouſly in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, they ſhall receive ſuch Encouragement from them, as the neeeſſity of preſerving ſo Important a Trade to the Nation, doth require.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
